大家好 我是《天天太空人》的Tim Dodd
Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd. The Everyday Astronaut.
火箭发动机 如此复杂
Rocket engines are incredibly complex machines,
不断在推进材料学与人类智慧的极限
pushing the boundaries of material science and human ingenuity.
而实际上 有相当多驱动火箭发动机运转的方法
And there's a wide range of ways you can actually power a rocket engine and make it work.
可以简单到一个高压储罐打开阀门就能用
They can be super simple, like just opening the valves of a tank that's under high pressure
也可以复杂到各种泵纵横交错在一起
to having complex pumps arranged in a fashion so confusing.
能有人想到如何制造它们 堪称智慧的奇迹
It's a miracle, anyone ever figured out how to build them in the first place.
本期视频其实标题应该叫《火箭发动机工作原理》
This video should really just be called "how rocket engines work"
或《如何驱动火箭发动机》
or "how you power rocket engines",
因为正是发动机的动力循环方式定义了它属于哪种发动机
because an engine's cycle type or its power cycle is really what defines the engine.
而现实中又有那么多的循环种类 想要记全真的很难
And there's so many different cycle types, it's really hard to keep track of them all.
就好像弄清活塞发动机里自然吸气 氮气加速 涡轮增压和机械增压的区别一样
It's like knowing the difference between a piston engine that's naturally aspirated,
hopped up on nitrous, turbocharged or supercharged.
它们都采用了相同的基本原理
Now they all operate under the same basic principles,
但为了实现不同的功率与效率指标采用了不同的技术
but they employ different techniques to reach power and or efficiency goals.
如果你看过我之前讲猛禽发动机的视频
av57059171
For those of you who have seen my Raptor engine video,
那么本期视频看起来会比较熟悉
some of this might be a review and familiar.
我还会像以前一样为大家带来简化后易于理解的图表
We're still going to be drawing out those same,
super simple and easy to understand diagrams, just like before,
只是这次将更加深入地了解所有主流的发动机循环
only this time we're going deeper and we're going over all the major engine cycles.
因为大家可能像我一样在那期视频之后
Because maybe you were like me and after that video,
还是不能理解全流量相比闭式的优势何在
you still couldn't quite grasp why full flow was advantageous over just closed cycle,
或者你还不了解抽气循环或膨胀循环
or maybe you don't know what tap-off is or expander cycle.
那你可得好好看看这期视频了
Well, here's your chance to really dive into this topic.
本期视频我们将带大家了解冷气推进 挤压循环 电动泵循环
So today we're going to talk about cold gas, pressure-fed, electric pump fed,
开式循环 闭式循环 全流量分级燃烧循环
open cycle, closed cycle, full flow stage combustion cycle,
抽气循环与膨胀循环
tap-off and expander cycles.
带大家了解各种循环方式的优劣与实例
We'll go over their pros and cons and lots of examples of each one.
如果你更喜欢阅读文章 想了解具体参考出处
And if you're more of a reader and want some links and sources,
本视频还在everydayastronaut.com上有文章版
we've got an article version of this video up at everydayastronaut.com
视频简介区也有链接
There is a link to that in the description as well.
掌握了火箭发动机循环方式 大家就能更好地了解这个时代的火箭发动机了
Rocket engine cycles, master this topic, and you'll have a really good grasp on rocket engines period.
我们开始吧
So let's get started.
开始之前 我想先向大家介绍这款超帅的全流量分级燃烧循环帽衫与衬衫
Right up top, I wanted to remind you that we do have this awesome
full flow stage combustion cycle hoodie, as well as shirts
以及在网店里的各种其他酷炫周边
and lots of other cool schematic shirts up at everydayastronaut.com/shop.
另外 在观看本期视频之前
And another quick note, a great video to watch before for this one
强烈建议先去看看这期《火箭发动机冷却方法介绍》
av723951018
would be my "Why don't rocket engines melt?" video,
里面有几种不同的发动机冷却技术与概念 在本视频中会有提及
because we do talk about a few of the different cooling techniques and concepts in this video.
如果没看过 建议看本视频前先去看看那个
So if you haven't watched that video consider watching it before you watch this one.
这两期视频都看完之后
And after having watched both of these videos,
我相信你对火箭发动机的了解会上一个台阶
I think you're going to have a great start on understanding rocket engines better than ever before.
我未来还会继续完善这个系列
And I'll have even more to add to this series like
比如如何启动火箭发动机 喷注器如何工作等
how to start a rocket engine and how injectors work.
我将继续把这些太空知识掰开了揉碎了带到地球上的大家
So, I'm getting back down to the roots of bringing space down to earth for everyday people.
希望大家开心
It's gonna be fun.
今天我们将了解火箭发动机的循环方式
But today we're talking about rocket engine cycles.
首先先大体了解一下火箭发动机的工作原理
So first let's talk about how they work in general.
火箭发动机的工作原理非常简单
A rocket engine functions under a simple concept,
即在一段时间内 以尽量快的速度向后抛射物质
throw stuff out the back as fast as possible, period.
抛射得越多 且抛射得越快
The more stuff you can throw and the quicker you can shoot it out,
就能产生更多的推力
the more thrust you can produce.
产生的推力越多 能推动的燃料与载荷就越多
The more thrust you can produce, the more stuff like fuel and payload you can lift.
这样才有可能在太空飞得越远
And the further you can potentially go in space.
抛射尾气的速度称为排气速度
The speed of your exhaust is known as exhaust gas velocity,
它不但与火箭可以产生的推力正相关
and it's not only directly related to the thrust that pushes back on the vehicle,
还与发动机的效率成正比
but it's also directly proportional to the efficiency of the engine.
所以排气速度越快越好
So the faster we throw propellant out the back, the better.
就像枪或大炮产生后坐力一样
Just like the recoil from a gun or a cannon.
它们的基础都是牛顿第三定律
That's the basic concept at play here, Newton's Third Law.
两物体相互作用 彼此施加的力 大小相等 方向相反
For each action there's an equal and opposite reaction.
只是在火箭上我们射出去的不是子弹或炮弹 而是无数速度极快的气体分子
Only instead of bullets or cannon balls, we're shooting tiny molecules of gas at ridiculously high velocities.
实现方法是将火箭发动机燃烧室内的压力和更重要的热量(这点比较反直觉)
The way to do that is by converting pressure and though non intuitively much more important, heat,
通过"拉瓦尔喷管" 或"收敛-扩张喷管"转化为动能
inside the combustion chamber of a rocket engine into kinetic energy
through what's known as a "de Laval nozzle", or a converging diverging nozzle,
将高温亚音速高压气体转化为低温超音速低压气体
which converts hot subsonic, high pressure gas
into cooler, supersonic, lower pressure gas.
其中的难点是让燃烧室内的压力与温度尽量高
The challenge is getting the pressure and temperature as high as possible in the combustion chamber
同时还要控制好热量
while managing the heat.
但总体而言 燃烧室内温度越高越好
But in general, the higher the temperature inside the combustion chamber, the better.
有了热量 啥都好办 因为热量就是能量
We can perform a lot of work with that heat because heat is energy.
一个体系中包含的所有能量称为"焓"
All the energy contained in a system is known as Enthalpy.
焓=体积×压强+内能 在这里就是热能
Enthalpy is volume times pressure plus energy, or in this case, heat energy.
所以体系里的焓越高 做功的潜力就越大
So really the higher the enthalpy is in the system, the more potential it has to perform work.
并且热能对焓影响巨大
And heat energy has a huge effect on Enthalpy.
我们还要记住一条重要规则
And there's one more important rule we need to remember,
流体总是从高压向低压流动
pressure always flows in a system from high to low.
如果流体某处的压力比在管路或燃料罐等处的压力更高
So if you have pressure anywhere,
that's higher pressure than the pipe or the tube or tank or whatever it's connected to,
那它总会流向压力更低的区域
it will always flow to the low pressure region.
我会在图表中标记压力与温度的大致数值
We'll label our diagrams with very rough pressure and temperature numbers,
便于大家对于体系中两者的变化有个大致概念
so you can get an idea of how they're changing throughout the system.
这也是工程师们实际在做的事情
This is a thing engineers actually do.
他们会根据需要多少压力来设计系统
They'll design a system and have a pressure budget based on how much pressure they need to create
从而保证一切流体向着正确的方向流动
in order to keep everything flowing in the right direction.
请大家通篇务必记住这个概念
So keep all of this in mind throughout this video,
你就会理解为什么工程师们要花这么大的力气
and you'll have an understanding of why engineers go to such great lengths
设计出这样令人眼花缭乱又心驰神往的"火箭科学"的殿堂
and design incredibly confusing Labyrinth, all in the name of rocket science.
火箭发动机最简单的形式
The simplest form of a rocket engine
就是在燃料罐内以很高的压力储存燃料
is just to simply store propellant in a tank at very high pressure,
打开一个阀门 让流体流向发动机 搞定!
open a valve and let that pressure flow into the engine, done!
这就是冷气推进发动机的基本原理
This is the basis of the cold gas rocket engine.
顾名思义 发动机是运行在相对低温状态的
As the name suggests the engine runs cold,
发动机内部没有燃烧或其他化学反应发生
meaning there is no chemical reaction or combustion that occurs,
单纯是储存的高压气体膨胀后流经喷管产生推力的过程
just simply the expansion of a stored gas, through the nozzle, to produce thrust.
称为冷气推进 单纯是因为气体在膨胀的时候温度会随之降低
And the name is literal because when expanding a gas, the temperature drops too,
即"焦耳-汤姆孙效应"
and that's called the Joule–Thomson effect.
所以它从物理上讲就是"冷"气推进发动机
So it actually is physically a cold gas thruster.
冷气推进发动机的最大局限就是体系内缺少热量与可用的压力
So the biggest limitation with a cold gas thruster is the lack of heat,
and the available pressure in the system.
别忘了那条规则 流体总是从高压流向低压
Remember our rule, pressure flows from high to low.
所以为了得到足够的压力让发动机产生足够推力
So in order to get high amounts of pressure and therefore thrust in the engine,
燃料罐内的压力就要比发动机内还高
it means the pressure in the tank always needs to be higher than it is in the engine.
所以可以想象 燃料罐内储存燃料的压力就要越高越好
As you can imagine, this means you'll want to store the propellant inside your tank
as high of pressure as possible
能塞多少塞多少
shove, just as much of it in there as you can,
但储存燃料的压力越高
but the higher the pressure you store your propellant,
燃料罐的厚度与重量也会随之增加
the thicker and heavier your tanks will need to be.
但毕竟这是火箭科学
And this is rocket science after all,
厚重的燃料罐在绝大多数情况下都不是什么好事
so thick and heavy tanks, aren't really a great option for most applications.
所以经过权衡会发现 耐高压但过于厚重的燃料罐其实并不值得
At some point, a trade-off occurs
where thicker and heavier tanks with higher pressure don't actually pay off
体系中过了某个值后 再去追求更高压力反而越亏
and it's not worth it anymore to pursue a higher pressure in the system.
所以工程师们转而研究能承受尽可能高压力 但又能尽可能轻巧的燃料罐
So great lengths go into making tanks hold as high of pressure as possible
while being as lightweight as they can.
常见的生产轻质高压储箱的工艺是COPV
A common method for making lightweight high pressure tanks is by using COPVs
即"复合材料缠绕压力容器"
or composite over-wrapped pressure vessels.
使用碳纤维或凯夫拉等复合材料紧紧缠绕金属储箱
COPVs are metal tanks wrapped really tightly with composites, such as carbon fiber or kevlar,
从而让燃料罐在高压下不会炸开
in order to basically keep them from bursting under extremely high pressures,
COPV通常可以耐受300-400bar的压力
COPVs typically operate at pressures around 300 or 400 bar,
而有些甚至可以达到800bar左右
but some can get up to around 800 bar even,
同样从名字看
and as the name implies,
冷气推进通常是气态燃料
a cold gas thruster are often gaseous propellants,
比同样能充满燃料罐的液体燃料密度要小很多
which are less dense than a liquid propellant filled tank.
但可以选择氮气或丁烷 它们在加压后可以以液体形式储存
However, nitrous or butane can be used, which are stored in liquid form under pressure.
当然 密度较小的燃料意味着它还需要更大更重的罐体来容纳同质量的燃料
And of course, a less dense propellant means it requires again,
even bigger and heavier tanks to hold the same relative mass of propellant,
最终让你的载荷运载能力大打折扣
which has a bad runaway effect and ultimately takes away from your payload capacity in a hurry.
冷气推进发动机通常使用氦气或氮气
Cold gas thrusters typically use helium or nitrogen
它们可压缩性强 相对分子量低
for their high compressibility and relatively low molecular weight,
可以以更高的速度喷出
which means they can be thrown out at greater velocities.
氢气或其他气体理论上也可以使用
Hydrogen or other propels could also be used,
但我真的没找到合适的例子
but I haven't really seen any good examples of those.
由于体系中压力与温度都很低
Now because the pressure and the temperature are low in the system,
冷气推进发动机的比冲 或者说效率也很低
the specific impulse or the efficiency of a cold gas thruster is low.
通常比冲只有60秒左右
It's usually only around 60 seconds of specific impulse,
只有最基本的泵压发动机的三分之一到四分之一
which is three or four times lower than even the most basic pump fed engine,
因为燃料从罐体内的高压一路膨胀到在喷管处的低压
because they're going from high pressure inside a tank, to low pressure as it expands out the nozzle,
你会发现体系会受制于燃料最多能膨胀多少才能不会在喷管内重新凝结
you can actually run into a limit on how much you can expand the nozzle
before you start turning your gas into a liquid while still in the nozzle.
而我们并不希望它重新凝结
And that's not good.
因此 这再次成为冷气推进发动机的另一巨大局限 总焓值过低
So again, that's actually another huge limitation of cold gas thrusters is just in the overall enthalpy
或者说体系内缺乏热能
or really the lack of heat in the system,
导致该种发动机很难做到高效率
which prevents them from really being that efficient.
但冷气推进发动机结构非常简单 极其可靠 只有一个活动部件
However, they're very simple and extremely reliable and really only have one moving part,
一个简单的阀门 仅此而已
a simple valve, that's about it.
而且虽然其效率不高 但结构简单 部件少 重量轻
And despite their low efficiency, because of their simplicity and lack of parts and weight,
有时它们会成为小卫星或立方星等小型航天器的最佳选择
sometimes they're actually the best choice for really small spacecraft like small sats or cubesats.
因为仔细想来 有些零件真的没法再缩了
Because think about it, there's some things you just can't really shrink down that much more,
就一个阀门的发动机你还想怎么缩
like a valve can only really get so small.
所以要是装上三五个的 这加一起数量就不少了
So if you have to have two of those or four of those or whatever, that adds up in a hurry.
冷气推进发动机的另一个例子是猎鹰九号火箭级间段上的小型调姿发动机
Another example of cold gas thrusters are the little tiny maneuvering thrusters
on the interstage of the Falcon 9 rocket
利用氮气 让一级火箭在着陆时保持正确朝向
that reorient the booster and help guide it to its landing point using nitrogen.
还有一个例子是在三次航天飞机任务中使用过的载人机动装置
Another example was that MMU or the Manned Maneuvering Unit that was used on three Space Shuttle missions.
没错 就是那个火箭喷气背包
Yeah, you know what I'm talking about, the rocket jet pack.
仅靠两个燃料罐内的18千克氮气驱动24个冷气推进发动机
That thing had 24 cold gas thrusters stored in just two propellant tanks
with about 18 kilograms of gaseous nitrogen.
但如果我们不直接把高压气体挤压进发动机
But now what if, instead of just having that high pressure gas flow straight to the engine,
而是找两种挤压出来后接触发生反应提供压力的燃料呢?
we instead had it pressurized and pushed out another propellant,
that could react and expand to offer higher performance.
嗯 这招可以一试
Well, that's definitely an option.
下一种结构简单的发动机叫"挤压循环发动机"
The next most simple engine design is called a pressure fed engine.
与冷气推进发动机类似 几乎没有移动部件 只有一些阀门
This is similar to a cold gas thruster in that it has almost no moving parts, just some valves,
却能通过引发燃料的化学反应提供相对更高的性能
but it can all offer much higher performance by tapping into the chemical reaction of the propellants.
挤压循环发动机有两种常见类型 只使用一种燃料的单组元发动机
There's two common types of pressure fed engines, mono-propellant, otherwise known as monoprop
和使用两种燃料的双组元发动机
or dual or bipropellant engines, otherwise known as biprop.
先说单组元发动机
So let's start off with monoprop engines.
单组元发动机和冷气推进发动机很像
A monoprop engine is a lot like a cold gas thruster,
但它除了一个燃料罐外
but instead of just a single tank,
还有一个装有惰性气体的高压储箱 通常是氦气或氮气
there's a high pressure tank with an inert gas, usually helium or nitrogen,
而低压储箱内的燃料通常是肼
and a lower pressure tank with a propellant, often hydrazine.
想要启动发动机 只需打开通往发动机的阀门并维持燃料罐压力即可
When you want to run your engine,
you just simply open the main valve to the engine and maintain pressure in your propellant tank
期间需要调节加压罐与燃料罐之间的阀门 也叫压力调节器
by modulating another valve also known as a regulator between the pressurant tank and the fuel tank.
就这么简单
It really is about that simple.
而单组元发动机的成功之处就在于将燃料中的一些化学能
Then the secret to monoprop's success is converting some chemical energy in the fuel
通过一些能量反应转换成热能与压力
into pressure and heat through some kind of energetic reaction.
没错 只靠燃料流经催化剂就能触发能量反应
That's right, you can actually have an energetic reaction with just your fuel running over a catalyst.
因此 假如使用一种易反应的燃料和一种强还原剂反应
So if you use a fuel that reactive and a strong reducing agent,
比如用过氧化氢或肼
such as hydrogen peroxide or hydrazine,
流经高锰酸钾或铱氧化铝催化剂床
and you run it against a catalyst bed like potassium permanganate, or iridium infused allumina,
就可以引发化学反应 产生压力与热量
you can harness that chemical reaction to create pressure and heat.
可如果产生了压力与热量
But wait, if we're creating pressure and heat,
如何保证它们不会倒流回去呢?
how does that not just go backwards up the system?
别忘了催化剂床的一侧有高压顶着
Well, don't forget there's high pressure pushing in on one side of the catalyst bed
而另一侧的喷管则是几乎完全敞口的状态
and basically an open hole through the nozzle on the other side.
所以物质会倾向于流向低压的喷管区 而不会倒流回高压区的喷注器
So that high pressure will want to flow out the nozzle to low pressure
easier than the high pressure at the injector.
但我们还要有更高的压力将燃料推进催化剂床
But we also have to have even higher pressure pushing that fuel into the catalyst bed.
所以我们还需要一个高压的COPV储箱储存大量高压气体
And here's where we still have to have a very high pressure COPV
storing a lot of high pressure gas in our pressurant tank.
这时还要考虑喷管的喉部可以做多大
Now a lot of thought also goes into just how big to make the throat of a nozzle
因为喉部的大小可以决定燃烧室内会产生多大的压力
as the size of the throat basically lets us know how much pressure will build up
inside the combustion chamber.
所以如果喉部太小 就会有倒流的风险
So if the throat is too small, there actually is a risk of pressure going back up the system.
这当然很不好
And of course that is bad.
但好的方面 我们现在可以在燃料罐内使用更致密的液体燃料了
But another good thing is now we can use a denser liquid propellant in our fuel tank
并且燃料罐的压力可以相对没那么高
and keep that fuel tank at relatively low pressure.
只要稍微比发动机内高就行了
It just has to be higher pressure than the engine.
所以随着液体燃料的消耗
So as liquid fuel is drained out,
加压罐的气体会不断填充燃料罐内的空间 维持燃料罐压力
we backfill the voids and keep that fuel tank pressurized with the pressurant tank.
这样一来 效率有以下几点提升
So we gain efficiency in a few ways here.
首先是用上了致密的液体燃料
First we gain the density increase of being able to use liquid propellants,
同样质量的燃料可以使用更小的储箱
which means much smaller tanks for the same mass of fuel.
同时还不需要让燃料处于非常高压的空间中
We don't need all of our fuel to be stored at crazy high pressure,
这样可以减轻储箱的重量
which means they can also be stored in lighter tanks.
我们还可以释放燃料中的化学能 产生热量
And we can unleash the chemical energy inside the fuel to create heat.
综上 单组元发动机的比冲 或者说效率 一般是冷气推进发动机的两到三倍
This leads to monoprop engines being typically about two to three times higher specific of a impulse
or more efficient than a simple cold gas thruster,
这也让它们成为调姿发动机的绝佳选择
which generally makes them a great choice for reaction control thrusters
还适用于其他对发动机简单可靠性需求较高的情景
or other engines where simplicity and reliability matter most.
举例来说 很多卫星上的调姿发动机
Some good examples of monoprop engines are the reaction control thrusters on many satellites
和联盟号飞船 水星号飞船的调姿发动机都是用的单组元发动机
or the reaction control thrusters on the Soyuz spacecraft as well as the Mercury capsule.
可如果我们还需要更高的性能呢?
But what if we still need higher performance?
那还有另一种结构相对简单的挤压循环发动机
Well, there's another type of pressure fed system that is still relatively simple,
效率还能更上一层楼
but can offer even higher efficiency,
双组元发动机
the bipropellant pressure fed engine.
双组元发动机和单组元发动机本质上非常接近
Bipropellant pressure fed engines are basically the same as a monoprop engine,
只是从一组加压罐和燃料罐变成了两组
but instead of just one propellant and pressurant tank, there's a pair of them.
一组储存燃料一组储存氧化剂
One set stores the fuel and the other set stores the oxidizer,
它们的工作方式类似
but they work together in a similar fashion.
结构仍然很简单 只要操控几个阀门即可运行
They still are very simple and rely only on a few valves opening to actually operate.
两个阀门分别将燃料和氧化剂输送给发动机
A pair of valves will open the fuel and the oxidizer tanks to the engine,
同时另外两个阀门负责用加压罐调整燃料罐的压力
and then another set of valves maintain adequate pressure
from the pressurant tanks to each of the propellant tanks.
双组元系统的优势是可以使用更高效的燃料 释放更多能量
The advantage of a biprop system is you can utilize a more energetic and efficient propellant.
实际上只要你想 你甚至可以选择更常见的燃料 比如煤油或甲烷
In fact, you could even run a fairly conventional propellant such as RP-1 or methalox
if that's what you wanted to do.
而很多双组元系统都会使用自燃燃料
But many bipropellant systems will utilize hypergolic propellants
两种燃料接触之后就会发生爆炸
or those that will spontaneously combust when they come in contact with each other.
这样可以让双组元系统极其简单可靠
This makes it so the bipropellant system can be the ultimate in simplicity and reliability
又能有非常不错的性能
while still offering decent performance.
不过到头来 发动机的性能还是会受到体系内总压力的限制
At the end of the day, you're still limited in your performance
by the total amount of pressure in the system.
为了不发生倒流 发动机内的压力只能这么高
You can only get so much pressure in the engine as you have upstream.
因此加压罐就永远是你的限制因素
So the pressurant tanks are still your limiting factor with a limited quantity.
就像冷气推进发动机 或所有挤压循环系统一样
And just like cold gas thrusters, or any of the pressure fed systems,
在到达某个压力后 继续增加压力已经无法弥补重量的增加了
at some point, the trade-offs of getting a higher pressure in the system
increases the weight so much that is just not worth it.
实际上 从未有过完全使用挤压循环发动机的火箭入轨
In fact, a fully and only pressure fed rocket has never made it to orbit.
也就是说 火箭所有分级 无论助推还是上面级 如果都使用挤压循环
So in other words, all stages, if you had your booster and your upper stages all pressure fed,
那它就没法入轨
none of them have ever made it to orbit.
传统认为 即使使用轻量级碳纤维复合材料储箱和其它新技术
By most conventions, even with lightweight carbon composite tanks and other new age tricks,
因为整体性能有限 火箭也不太可能做到入轨
it's considered basically impossible due to its limited overall performance.
但有一家公司找到了解决办法 那就是萤火虫公司
But one company did have a solution, that was Firefly.
他们的阿尔法火箭设计上使用的是塞式发动机
Their original Alpha design was going to utilize an aerospike engine
用来克服挤压循环系统的种种限制
to overcome some of the limitations of a pressure fed system.
他们认为可以借此做到入轨
And they thought that thing could make it to orbit.
在萤火虫 我们研发了一款碳纤维挤压循环发动机
In Firefly space systems we were developing a, a carbon fiber pressure fed rocket.
对于挤压循环发动机 想要达到足够室压
So on a pressure fed rocket to get that chamber pressure,
就要让储箱的压力足够高
you have to pay for it in the pressure of the tanks.
-就要让储箱加厚
Which means thicker tanks.
-没错 非常非常厚的储箱 所以对于挤压循环发动机来说
Thicker thicker tanks, so in the pressure fed rocket,
我们要想办法降低燃料罐的压力
you're really trying to lower the pressure in the propellant tanks.
话虽如此 还是有很多火箭在上面级选择了挤压循环发动机
But that being said, many rockets have utilized pressure fed upper stages,
比如SpaceX的猎鹰一号火箭上面级的Kestrel发动机
such as SpaceX's Falcon 1 upper stage with the Kestrel engine,
或者Astra火箭二级的Aether发动机
or Astra's Aether engine on their second stage.
但最好最直观的双组元挤压循环系统的例子还得数航天飞机的轨道机动系统
But the Space Shuttle's OMS pods or the Orbital Maneuvering System
is maybe the best and most simplified look at a bipropellant pressure fed system.
我们能清楚看到两个加压罐 一个燃料罐一个氧化剂罐
We can clearly see the two pressurant tanks, a fuel tank and an oxidizer tank.
教科书版的摆放
All right, there laid out perfectly.
虽然在发射级上用得不多
Now, despite not being as commonly used on launch vehicles,
但在调姿发动机上却非常常见
it's extremely common for reaction control thrusters,
美国几乎每一个航天器上都有应用
and you'll see it used on almost every United States spacecraft
从航天飞机到SpaceX的载人龙飞船
from the Space Shuttle, to SpaceX's Crew Dragon capsule,
从阿波罗指令舱和服务舱 甚至到更远古的双子座飞船
to the Apollo Command and Service Module, or even the Gemini capsule.
挤压循环发动机有巨大的限制
Pressure fed engines have a big limiting factor.
即只有增加油箱的重量 才能提高体系中的压力
And that's the weight of the tanks increases, the higher the pressure in the system is.
那么可否不用高压笨重的储箱
So what if instead of having high pressure, heavy tanks,
改用低压轻质的储箱 使用一个泵把燃料怼进发动机呢?
you used low pressure, lightweight tanks and used a pump to shove propellant into the engine.
虽然实际做起来很复杂
Well, although that can get really complicated,
但有一套系统可以做得非常简单
there's one system that's extremely simple.
好 我们决定用泵把燃料打进发动机
Okay, so we want to pump our propellants into the engine.
众所周知 泵可以大大增加压力
Obviously, a pump can increase the pressure a lot,
而我也提到过 压力可是个好东西
and as we know, pressure is a good thing.
但泵的运转需要能量 相当相当多的能量
But running a pump requires energy, a lot of energy.
所以驱动一个泵最简单的方法 就是用电
So perhaps the easiest way to power a pump is with electricity.
没错 这在航天领域已经变成现实了
That's right. That is now a reality in spaceflight.
可以用锂电池驱动电动泵 将燃料加压后输送给火箭发动机
You can run a rocket engine with pressure from a pump run by an electric motor
powered by a lithium battery.
现在开始有点变得复杂了
So now we're adding a little bit of complexity,
但最大的好处是可以降低燃料罐的压力了
but our biggest advantage is now we can lower the pressure inside the tanks.
压力可以从原来的30bar左右降低到现在只有大约3bar
We can go from something like 30 bar down to only about 3 bar of pressure.
随之而来储箱重量的降低可想而知
And as you can imagine, that makes the tanks much, much lighter.
只要储箱节约下来的重量比泵 电机 电池组的重量大
So as long as the weight saved on tanks
is lighter than the weight of the pumps, motors and batteries,
那我就赢麻了
it's a win.
但即使有了超轻复合材料储箱和最高能量密度最高效的电池
But even with super lightweight composite tanks and the most energy dense and efficient batteries,
你这个系统的尺度也是很有限的
there's a limit to how big you can scale up the system.
泵需要消耗成吨的功率
Pumps can require thousands of horsepower.
RD-170发动机的功率是170兆瓦 23万马力
In fact, the RD-170's pumps require 170 MW of power or 230,000 HP.
你想想这得要多大的电动机?
Imagine having an electric motor that big!
这是LUCID AIR的动力单元
This is LUCID AIR's motor unit.
重74千克 输出功率约500千瓦
It weighs 74 kilograms and puts out about 500 kilowats,
算是现在能找到的最先进的电机了
and it's one of the most advanced motors you can find today.
想要驱动RD-170的泵 需要340台这样的电机
It would require roughly 340 of these motors to power the pumps of the RD-170.
每台74千克 那么电动机的总重就是25.16吨
And at 74 kilograms, we're looking at about 25,160 kilograms just for the motors to spin the pumps.
没错 光是驱动泵的电动机就已经是整个RD-170发动机重量的2.5倍了
So yeah, just the motors alone to power the pumps
would be about two and a half times heavier than an entire RD-170.
这还没算上电池的重量 而且电池并不会随着放电而变轻
That's not including the weight of the batteries, which don't get lighter as they drain their charge.
所以还得准备几吨的电池驱动它
So we'd need several additional tons of batteries in order to power this.
更别提电池的能量密度只有煤油的50到100分之一
And that's not even taking into account the power density of batteries,
which is 50 to 100 times less power dense than RP-1.
因此 即使你大大优化了电机和电池的重量
So even if you optimized a motor and batteries to be substantially lighter,
甚至已经达到了高性能电车重量的一半
maybe even half the weight of those on a high performance electric vehicle,
也仍然比燃料驱动的涡轮泵重得多 功率密度低得多
we're still looking at something a lot heavier and less power dense than a turbine and propellant.
由于这些限制 电动泵供能火箭一直认为是现实中不可能做到的
Because of these limitations, electric pump fed rockets were actually considered impossible,
直到最近 由于电池技术终于满足了需求
until just recently, as battery technology is finally good enough
可以成为让火箭入轨的解决方案了 但也很勉强
to even make this a viable solution for an orbital launcher, but just barely.
火箭实验室在这道难题上有所突破
Rocket Lab pushed through that barrier,
成功制造了历史上第一款电动泵驱动的入轨级火箭——电子号
and it was successful in making the first electric pump fed orbital rocket in history, the Electron.
Astra公司也摸着他们的石头研发了Delphin发动机
Since they paved the way, Astra has followed in their footsteps with the Delphin engines
用在他们的火箭的一级上
on the first stage of their rockets as well.
电动泵也逐渐成为新火箭公司的热门选择
And it's become a popular choice for new rocket companies
因为研发简单 性能还比挤压循环系统高
because of its relative ease of development and higher performance than a pressure fed system.
但它仍然在性能上有诸多限制 无法驾驭大型火箭
That being said, it's still quite limited on performance
and it doesn't scale up well for larger launch vehicles.
那如果既想要性能 又想造大火箭怎么办?
So what if you need more performance, you're trying to make a larger launch vehicle?
我想是时候该用火箭燃料来驱动泵了
Well, I think it's time we tap into the energy of that rocket fuel to power our pumps.
刚刚提到 我们需要相当大的能量才能让泵运转到足够的速度
As we've mentioned, it can take a lot of energy to spin a big pump fast enough
才能把大量的燃料以足够高的压强泵入燃烧室
to flow ridiculous amounts of propellant into a combustion chamber at very high pressures.
虽然23万马力已经算功率需求的天花板了
Although 230,000 HP is at the upper end of the power requirements,
但对于多数入轨级火箭发动机来说 也得是上万马力这个数量级
tens of thousands of horsepower is still in the realm of most orbital rocket engines.
所以如果我们不用电动机驱动泵的话
So what if instead of having an electric motor spin the pumps,
改用一个小型火箭发动机对着涡轮吹
we basically take a small rocket engine and point it at a turbine
把它喷出的高速高压高温燃气转换成机械能
and allow that high velocity, high pressure, hot exhaust gas to perform mechanical work.
这正是开式循环 也叫燃气发生器循环的基本思路
Well that's the idea behind the open cycle, otherwise known as the gas generator cycle.
我们额外搞一个小型火箭发动机 让它专门产生高压高温燃气
You basically create a small rocket engine whose sole purpose is to generate high pressure hot gas
用来驱动发动机的燃料泵
that can be used to spin the pumps that feed the engine.
最早的应用实例是德国的V2火箭的A-4发动机
One of the earliest examples of this was the German designed V2 rocket with the A-4 engine.
他们没有使用火箭主发动机的燃料 而是使用一个单组元火箭来驱动泵
Instead of utilizing the main propellant, they basically used a monoprop rocket to spin the pumps.
使用浓缩的过氧化氢作为燃料
They chose high concentration hydrogen peroxide as the fuel,
让它流经高锰酸钾催化剂
and then they ran it over a potassium permanganate catalyst
就能创造足够多的能量 让涡轮达到足够高的转速
that can create enough energy to spin the turbine up to the right speeds.
我很欣赏这个解决方案 因为它使用了一个简单的挤压式单组元发动机
I like this solution because it's using a simple pressure fed monoprop rocket engine
来驱动功率更高的泵 从而提升发动机的整体输出
to spin a larger, more powerful pump to increase the overall output of the engine.
非常机智
It's a pretty clever idea.
而且至今在联盟号火箭的RD-107A和RD-108A发动机上仍在使用
And it's still in use today on the Soyuz rocket on the RD-107A and the RD-108A.
但另拿一组燃料罐来储存燃气发生器的燃料确实效率偏低
But that's a little less efficient to have another set of tanks for your gas generator fuel,
燃气发生器也只能得到来自单组元发动机的能量
and then you're also only getting the energy from a monoprop engine,
却得不到近在咫尺的火箭主发动机更高的能量
instead of just tapping into the high energy rocket fuel that's already right there inside the rocket.
因此 更复杂但性能也更高的办法
So a more sophisticated and higher performing option
是让燃气发生器直接使用火箭的主燃料
is to use the main propellants themselves inside the gas generator.
只取一点燃料与极少的氧化剂送入燃气发生器
So they'll take some of the fuel and just a dash of oxidizer and send it through the gas generator
来产生高温高压燃气 驱动涡轮
to create high pressure hot gas to power the turbine.
工程师会让燃烧过程极度富燃
They will run this combustion extremely fuel rich
因为看过我之前《火箭发动机冷却方法介绍》的朋友可能记得
av723951018
because as those of you that watch my, "Why don't rocket engines melt" video might know,
工程师需要保持燃气发生器温度足够低来防止其熔化并损伤涡轮
engineers keep the temperatures of the gas generator low enough to not melt and destroy the turbine.
燃气发生器的燃料也是它带动的泵供给的
The gas generator is fed from the pumps themselves,
所以燃气发生器内的压力非常高
so the pressure inside the gas generator can be really high,
需要不惜一切让涡轮达到转速 给泵供能
whatever it takes to get the turbines up to right speed to power the pumps.
但当然了 这里有个难点
But of course, this brings up a conundrum.
如果泵的动力来自燃气发生器
If the pumps are powered from the gas generator,
而燃气发生器的燃料又是来自于泵
and the gas generator is powered by the pumps,
那这个过程最开始该怎么启动?
how in the heck do you get this process started?
实际上火箭发动机的启动就是另外一个话题了
Well, starting a rocket engine is a whole different topic altogether.
以后我会另做一期视频专门讲这个内容
So we'll save that topic for another video.
但最常用的方法是用一个冷气推进发动机吹动涡轮
But the most common thing to do is just basically shoot a separate cold gas thruster at the turbine
涡轮先转起来 发动机才能启动
to get it spinning first, before the engine actually starts to run,
称为"氦气吹转启动"
and this is called a helium spin start.
燃气发生器驱动涡轮旋转后 所有的废气都被排放掉了
With a gas generator, all the exhaust gases that were used to spin the turbine
are simply dumped overboard,
或者用来冷却部分喷管
or perhaps maybe used to cool portions of the nozzle.
废气并没有被重新引入主燃烧室
But the gases are not added into the main combustion chamber.
因此这种循环称为"开式循环"
That's why this is called open cycle.
废气只是被排放到了空气或太空中
The exhaust gas is used and then it's expelled to the open air or space.
并没有参加主要的燃烧过程
It's not used in any part of the main combustion process.
开式循环的缺点就是会浪费大量未燃烧的燃料
The downside with the open cycle is that there's a ton of unburnt fuel in the exhaust.
看到燃气发生器排出的黑黑的废气了吗?
See how dark and sooty the exhaust from the gas generator can be?
全是没烧干净的燃料 就这么排掉了
That's unburnt fuel just being wasted and thrown away.
开式循环会浪费一部分燃料来驱动泵
So the open cycle wastes some of the propellant in order to power the pumps.
但总体而言还是值得的
But generally it's considered worth it
因为相比于主燃烧室使用的燃料来说 浪费的还是相对少数
because it is a relatively small amount of fuel
compared to the amount of fuel used inside the combustion chamber.
使用燃气发生器的开式循环发动机实例有SpaceX猎鹰九号的Merlin1D发动机
Some good examples of gas generator, open cycle engines are the Merlin 1D engines on SpaceX's Falcon 9,
土星五号的F-1和J-2发动机
the F-1 and J-2 engines on the Saturn V,
刚刚提到的联盟号的RD-107A和RD-108A发动机
the RD-107A and RD-108A as we mentioned on the Soyuz,
德尔塔IV的普通型也用RS-68发动机
德尔塔IV重型上的RS-68发动机 此外还有相当多的例子
the RS-68 on the Delta-IV Heavy and many, many others.
开式循环以其高效 能力强 相对其他更复杂的循环更易研发的特性
It's easily one of the most common cycle types for orbital rockets,
being extremely effective, highly capable,
轻松成为入轨级火箭最常用的循环类型
and relatively easy to develop compared to other more exotic cycle types.
但如果性能还不够呢?
But what if it's not enough?
如果开式循环还是没有达到想要的性能
What if you're still not hitting your target performance
听说浪费燃料之后还想一哭二闹三上吊怎么办?
and you're crying at the thought of wasting fuel and dumping it overboard?
那我们能不能用某种方法把燃气泵回发动机 不再浪费分毫呢?
Well, what if we could somehow pump that exhaust right back into the engine,
and not waste any fuel?
闭式循环 或分级燃烧循环
The closed cycle or staged combustion cycle,
火箭工程师们在察觉到它理论上潜在的超高性能后都想很快驾驭它
something rocket engineers quickly sought to try to master
after seeing the potential for incredibly high performance.
闭式循环并不是简单把燃气发生器废气直接送入主燃烧室就撒手不管了
In the closed cycle, they don't just attach the gas generator exhaust pipe to the main combustion chamber
and cross their fingers.
后果很严重 原因如下
That would be very bad for a few reasons.
流经涡轮后
The pressure run through the turbine is usually kept to a minimum
压力通常会降低到一个很低的值
绝大部分压力都用来驱动涡轮了
and we lose most of that pressure to spin the turbine.
所以主燃烧室的燃气
So the main combustion chamber gases would want to go backwards through the system.
很可能会逆流回系统中
我们显然不希望如此
And of course that's not good.
但如果你用的是煤油等碳基燃料
But also if you're using RP-1 or any other carbon based fuel,
充满煤烟的废气对喷注器和再生通道等一切都是毁灭性的
that sooty exhaust is terrible for injectors and regen channels and all sorts of things.
发动机很可能会在一瞬间熄火报废
So you'd likely clog your engine up, and it would cease to function in a hurry.
首先 我们不是只用一点燃料和氧化剂来运行燃气发生器
First off, instead of just using a little fuel and oxidizer to run the gas generator,
而是将所有燃料或氧化剂通过燃气发生器与涡轮
we'll actually put all of the fuel or oxidizer through the gas generator, and the turbine.
此时它也不再叫"燃气发生器"
And now we won't call it a gas generator.
而是"预燃室" 因为它的功能正如其名
It'll actually be considered a preburner because that's exactly what we'll be doing.
预先燃烧一点燃料
Pre-burning the propellant a little,
经过预燃后再进入主燃烧室进行充分燃烧
preburning it before it gets into the main combustion chamber for the real full burn.
再重复一遍 是让全部的燃料或全部的氧化剂流经预燃室和涡轮
Now, remember, again, we're going to be flowing either
all of our fuel or all of our oxidizer through the preburner and the turbine,
是燃料还是氧化剂 决定了是哪种闭式循环
and depending on which one it is, that's which type of closed cycle.
要么富燃 要么富氧
So either fuel rich, or oxidizer are rich.
我们先从最先出现的闭式循环——富氧闭式循环说起
Let's start off with the oxidizer rich closed cycle,
since it was the first closed cycle engine developed,
看过我的《苏联火箭发动机历史大全》的朋友可能有印象
av294439869
感谢@天外飞舰
as those of you who watched my "Complete guide to Soviet rocket engine history" would know.
苏联工程师早在1950年研发的S1.5400发动机就拿下了富氧分级燃烧
Soviet engineers were able to overcome the challenges of oxidizer rich stage combustion
苏联工程师早在五十年代研发的S1.5400发动机就拿下了富氧分级燃烧
in the late 1950s, already with the S1.5400.
苏联选择了富氧分级燃烧
The Soviets chose to go with the oxygen-rich stage combustion cycle
是因为使用煤油为主的RG-1或RP-1燃料会遇到结焦问题
because when running on kerosene based RG-1 or RP-1, you'd run into the coking and sooting issues.
因此他们决定让全部氧化剂流经涡轮
So this means they decided to run all of the oxidizer through the turbine,
之后把富氧燃气泵入主燃烧室
and then pipe that into the main combustion chamber.
其中只添加刚好够驱动泵达到转速 产生足够压力与热量的燃料
Then they inject just exactly as much fuel as they need
to make enough heat and energy to spin the pumps fast enough to create high enough pressure and heat,
因为别忘了对涡轮做功转化为机械能后压力会下降
because remember it will drop as it runs through the turbines as it's converted into mechanical work.
然后富氧燃气就会进入主燃烧室
And it then will go into the combustion chamber.
还记得"流体总是从高压流向低压"吗
And what's our rule, pressure always flows from high to low.
所以预燃室内的压力要比主燃烧室压力高
So the pressure inside the preburner needs to much higher than the combustion chamber.
这样流体经过涡轮和喷注器两次降低压力后
That way when the pressure drops across the turbine, and then drops again in the injector,
还能在相对安全的阈值内顺利进入主燃烧室
it's still coming into the main combustion chamber with some margin of safety.
通用的标准是流经预燃室和涡轮的压力是主燃烧室的两倍
A good rule of thumb is two times higher pressure from the preburner through the turbine
喷注器后方的压力比主燃烧室高20%
and about 20% higher pressure between the back of the injector and the chamber,
而工程师对发动机有信心的话还会进行更多的调试
but engineers tend to chew away at these as they gain confidence with an engine,
继续榨取更高的性能
and they try to pursue higher and higher performance.
现在一个终极问题来了
But now we have kind of the ultimate question,
你怎么能让预燃室的压力高于主燃烧室
how do you get the preburner to be higher pressure than the main combustion chamber?
在富氧分级燃烧循环中
In the oxidizer rich stage combustion cycle,
因为所有氧化剂都要流经涡轮 所以都会被加到非常非常高的压力
All of the oxidizer will get compressed up to very, very high pressure
since it all will flow through the turbine,
但对于燃料来说却并非如此
but that same thing isn't true for the fuel.
绝大多数燃料都直接泵入了主燃烧室
The majority of the fuel will just flow into the combustion chamber.
所以压力只要加到比燃烧室高20%就行了
So it only needs to be pressurized to about that 20% higher pressure than the combustion chamber,
但我们还需要一些足够高压的燃料去预燃室里做功
but we still need some of the fuel to be high enough pressure to power the preburner.
所以此时 泵被分成了多级
So in this case, there's actually stages to the pump.
绝大多数燃料流经第一级 达到足够压力后就泵进了主燃烧室
Most of the fuel will go through the first stage,
which gets it to be high enough pressure for the main combustion chamber,
而之后 一小部分燃料会继续进入第二级燃料泵
but then some of it will actually go into another stage of the pump
继续提高压力 供给预燃室
that increases the pressure to be high enough pressure for the preburner.
你可能会想 氧化剂已经在预燃室内经过燃烧了
Now you might be thinking, wait, the oxidizer has already been burnt in the preburner,
那它怎么能进主燃烧室又进行一次燃烧?
how can it be burnt up again in the main combustion chamber?
原因是之前只有一小部分燃料参与了反应
Well, since there was only a dash of fuel to react with,
绝大多数的氧化剂还并没有反应
the vast majority of oxidizer is unreacted.
已经遇热后从液体变成了气体
But it has warmed up from a liquid to a hot gas,
但在进入主燃烧室前仍然保留有大量的化学能
but it still has most of its chemical energy when it enters the main combustion chamber,
富氧燃气到了主燃烧室遇到大部分燃料
where it will then react with fuel,
进行燃烧过程 和燃料一起释放了其剩余的化学能
then the main combustion process happens, unleashing the remaining energy from the propellants.
富氧分级燃烧循环研发非常困难
The oxidizer rich stage combustion cycle is very very hard,
因为系统中出现了高温高压的富氧燃气
since you're creating high pressure, hot gas oxygen,
极度活泼易反应
which sure loves to react with absolutely everything.
需要非常强大的特种合金才能应付这种极端环境
It requires fancy metal alloys that can handle those extreme environments.
而苏联做到了 也让他们绝大多数发动机都用上了富氧分级燃烧循环
The Soviets mastered this as the majority of their engines were oxidizer rich staged combustion cycle,
包括N1火箭的NK-15和NK-33
including the NK-15 and NK-33's for the N1,
能源号的RD-170 宇宙神V的RD-180
the RD-170 on the Energia and the RD-180 on the Atlas V.
这个难度真的相当大
This is actually extremely difficult,
美国的所有入轨级火箭至今还没有用上本土制造
and something the United States still hasn't achieved for an orbital rocket.
不过很快蓝色起源的富氧闭式循环的液氧甲烷BE-4发动机
Although Blue Origin's BE-4 oxygen-rich closed cycle methalox engine
就要用在联合发射联盟的火神火箭和他们自家的新格伦火箭了
will fly on United Launch Alliance's upcoming Vulcan rocket, and Blue Origin's New Glenn rocket.
还有Launcher公司的液氧煤油E-2发动机
There's also Launcher's kerolox E-2 engine,
富氧闭式循环 性能很强
which is oxygen-rich closed cycle with impressive performance.
但在视频发布之时 这些发动机都还没有上过天
But neither engine has currently flown as of the making of this video,
希望它们能早日夺得美国首款自主研发的富氧闭式循环发动机的头衔吧
but hopefully they will soon and will take that title
of the first US built oxygen-rich closed cycle engine.
但美国并没有就这样放弃分级燃烧循环
But the United States didn't completely give up on staged combustion.
他们只是选择了另一条赛道
They just went the other way.
即富燃分级燃烧循环
They pursued fuel rich stage combustion,
并借此造就了航天飞机上强大的RS-25发动机
for an engine at the heart of an icon, the RS-25 on the mighty Space Shuttle.
如果我们把富氧分级燃烧循环里两者调换位置
What if we basically swapped the process of the oxidizer rich stage combustion cycle,
让所有燃料和一小部分氧化剂流经涡轮怎样?
and just put all of the fuel through the turbine, and just used a little oxidizer?
就像多数的燃气发生器工作时那样
Kind of like most gas generators.
那样不就不用应付高温氧气了吗?
Wouldn't that avoid the issues of having hot gaseous oxygen?
没错 是这样
Well, yes, yes it does.
但就像我们之前提到的 这样会遇到煤油结焦的问题
But as we mentioned, it brings up another problem, coking and soot.
那我们能不能不用煤油等高碳燃料呢?
But wait, what if we didn't use RP-1 or any other carbon rich fuel?
工程师设计航天飞机的主推进系统时选择了液氢和液氧
When engineers were designing the main propulsion system for the Space Shuttle,
they went with liquid hydrogen and liquid oxygen,
因为液氢可以以富燃的形式在预燃室内做功且不用担心结焦
because they can run hydrogen fuel rich through the preburners and not have it create soot,
发动机也能很轻松面对高温富氢气体
and the engine will happily run with hot gaseous hydrogen.
听起来很轻松就解决了 可不是这样
This seems like a pretty obvious solution, but wait,
富燃分级燃烧循环虽然不会结焦 但也会有自己独有的技术难点
fuel rich staged combustion cycle comes with its own challenges besides the potential for soot,
尤其对于氢来说
especially if you're using hydrogen.
液氢非常"非致密"
Hydrogen is extremely undsense.
有这词吗? "稀松"或者"轻量"?
I don't think that's a word, sparse or lightweight,
说白了就是密度低 很占储箱空间
which of course means it takes up a lot of space in tanks,
同时想要达到足够压力还需要非常庞大的分级燃料泵
but it also takes a large pumps with a lot of stages to get it to the right pressures.
最常见也可能是最简单的方法是让泵和涡轮共用一个轴
It's common and perhaps the most simple to have a single shaft for your pumps and your turbine,
前提是轴上元件都能以相同转速工作
assuming everything on that shaft can operate at similar speeds.
而且虽然的确出现过共轴的液氢液氧富燃闭式循环发动机
And although single shaft hydrolox fuel rich close cycle engines have been made,
比如苏联的能源号助推器上的RD-0120发动机
like the Soviet Union's RD-0120 at the heart of their Energia booster,
美国选择了另一个解决方案 同时也带来了新的问题
the US went with a different solution that raised its own set of problems.
他们设计的RS-25发动机使用了两个富燃的预燃室 驱动两个轮轴
Their design for the RS-25 called for dual preburners on two different shafts, both fuel rich,
一个预燃室驱动燃料泵 一个驱动氧化剂泵
one preburner would power the fuel pumps and the other would power the oxygen pumps.
但同一个轮轴一侧是高温富氢燃气
But having high pressure hot gaseous hydrogen in your preburner
另一侧是液氧 就很容易出事
on the same shaft as high pressure liquid oxygen is a recipe for disaster.
如果高温富氢燃气顺着轮轴漏过去遇到液氧
If any of that hot gaseous fuel would make its way up the shaft and meet oxygen,
就完犊子了
it would be game over.
所以美国工程师搞了这个极其复杂的氦吹气密封
So US engineers had to develop an extremely elaborate purge seal,
防止燃料顺着轮轴泄漏过去
that prevented propellant traveling up or down the shaft
办法就是把更高压力的氦气放在中间
by having even higher pressure inert helium in the middle of it.
就算有泄漏 也只是更高压力的氦气漏到预燃室或氧泵里
So if anything, leaks, it would leak out from that higher pressure helium side
and into the preburner or the oxygen pump.
回到示意图中
So looking at our diagram here,
两个轮轴连接起两个涡轮和预燃室 构成了富燃循环发动机
you can see the two separate turbines and preburners of a dual shaft fuel rich cycle engine.
一个预燃室驱动氧化剂泵 一个驱动燃料泵
Of course, one preburner powers the oxidizer pumps and the other powers the fuel pumps.
两个预燃室都是富燃燃烧
Since these preburners run fuel rich,
即所有燃料都会流经其中一个预燃室和涡轮
it means all of the fuel will go through one of the preburners and turbines
然后才会进入主燃烧室
before it goes into the main combustion chamber.
所以我们可以看到大约各有一半的燃料会流经一个预燃室和涡轮
So we see that approximately half of the fuel flows through each preburner and turbine.
与富氧闭式循环发动机完全相反
And exactly opposite of the oxidizer rich closed cycle engine,
只有一小部分氧化剂进入了预燃室
in this case only a dash of oxidizer goes into the preburners,
刚好足够产生驱动泵达到转速的能量
just enough to create enough energy to spin the pumps up to the right speeds
产生刚好够的压力 让燃料和氧化剂能进入预燃室和涡轮
to create the high pressure needed to get the propellant through the preburner and turbine
最后进入主燃烧室
and into the combustion chamber.
同样和富氧闭式循环发动机完全相反
And again, opposite the oxidizer rich closed cycle engines,
在富燃的例子中 多数氧化剂只经过一级泵压
in this case, most of the oxidizer will only go through a single stage pump
就能达到足够的压力进入主燃烧室
that gets it to be high enough pressure to go into the main combustion chamber.
而少部分进入预燃室的氧化剂则会进入二级氧化剂泵以达到足够高的压力
But the bit of oxidizer that goes into the preburners will flow through a second stage of pumps
to get it up to those higher pressures.
RS-25发动机是美国第一款闭式循环发动机
So the RS-25 was the United States' first closed cycle engine,
但并不是人类研发的唯一一款富燃发动机
but it wasn't the only fuel rich engine developed.
苏联研发的RD-56和RD-57 也都是富燃分级燃烧氢氧机
The Soviets also made the RD-56 and RD-57,
which were both fuel rich staged combustion hydrolox engines
用于N1火箭的升级版
developed for an upgraded N1 variant.
他们还有RD-0120发动机 用于能源号火箭的芯级
They also made the RD-0120, which was at the heart of the Energia rocket.
是苏联发射过的推力最大的单燃烧室火箭发动机
It's the most powerful single chambered rocket engine the Soviet union ever flew.
因此 富燃分级燃烧循环在泵的复杂度上做出妥协
So the fuel rich stage combustion cycle trades one bit of complexity for the other,
但即使这样 还有一种发动机结合了两种循环的优劣
but even so there's still one cycle type that combines many of the pros and cons of both cycle types
造就了发动机的终级复杂的形态
to form one ultimate and confusing engine,
但即使再复杂 它的优点 也值得那些艺高人胆大的工程师去冒这个险
but one pro makes it worth pursuing,
but only for those daring enough to try.
就你了 全流量分级燃烧循环发动机
Full flow staged combustion engines is exactly what it sounds like.
全流量 指全部燃料和氧化剂都会流经预燃室和涡轮
The full flow of propellant, so both the fuel and the oxidizer goes through a preburner and turbine.
两个预燃室一个富燃 一个富氧
This means there's both a fuel rich preburner and an oxidizer rich preburner.
我们先跟着燃料和氧化剂在泵和涡轮里走一遍
Let's first just follow the propellants as they go through the pumps and turbines.
两者以储箱压力来到泵的入口
Fuel and oxidizer arrive at the pump inlets at tank pressure.
然后泵把它们直接加压到预燃室的压力
Then the pumps take them up to the full preburner pressures.
让几乎所有氧化剂进入氧预燃室和涡轮
Then we take almost all of the oxidizer and run it through the oxidizer preburner and turbine,
只取适当的量送入富燃预燃室 产生驱动富燃侧涡轮的能量
but we do need to send just enough oxidizer over to the fuel rich preburner
to give it enough power to power that turbine.
富燃的一侧同理
And the same thing is true for the fuel rich side.
几乎所有燃料都会进入富燃预燃室和涡轮
Almost all of the fuel goes through the fuel rich preburner and turbine,
只取适当燃料送入富氧预燃室 产生驱动富氧侧涡轮的能量
but we do need to pipe over just enough fuel to the oxidizer rich preburner
to have enough energy to spin those pumps.
最终得到极度富燃的高温燃气
What's left is extremely fuel rich gaseous fuel
从富燃预燃室和涡轮出来进入主燃烧室
going from the fuel rich preburner and turbine to the combustion chamber.
还有极度富氧的高温氧化剂
Then we have extremely oxidizer rich gaseous oxidizers
从富氧预燃室和涡轮出来进入主燃烧室
going from the oxidizer rich preburner and turbine to the combustion chamber.
两者都会以高温气体的形式在主燃烧室内相遇
This means both propellants wind up in the combustion chamber in hot gaseous form.
这可以带来非常大的优势
And this is actually a huge advantage.
"气-气"混合反应相比"液-液""气-液"效率极高 燃烧更快更充分
A gas-gas interaction is extremely efficient and burns much quicker and more completely
than liquid-liquid or liquid-gas interactions.
正如伊龙·马斯克这样说道
Or as Elon Musk put it.
全流量分级燃烧 没错
Full flow stage combustion, exactly, uh,
里面发生的是气-气混合反应 两种高温气体相遇
you've got a gas gas interaction, so you've got two hot gases combining.
我们能达到90% 准确讲是98.5% 有希望达到99%的理论燃烧效率
We think we can probably get to 90, certainly 98 and a half,
hopefully 99% of theoretical combustion efficiency.
可能只有让老天爷亲自过来手把手把分子粘上才能完成剩下那1%吧
This is so if God himself came and knitted together the molecules, he could do 1% better,
就当剩下是1.5%吧 那也很高效啦
OK, maybe 1.5% better, that's how, that's very high efficiency.
毕竟是全流量分级燃烧循环
-Because of full flow stage combustion.
相信大家很快就能看出我们这时要同时解决
Right off the bat, we can already see we're having to deal with the problems of
富氧分级燃烧和富燃分级燃烧循环的所有难点
oxidizer rich stage combustion and fuel rich stage combustion cycle.
富氧侧需要能应付高温富氧燃气
So our oxidizer side has to be able to handle the problems of hot gaseous oxygen.
不过还好 我们至少可以用富氧的涡轮和轴来驱动氧泵
The good news is at least we can couple the oxidizer rich turbine and shaft with the oxidizer pump.
还可以用富燃预燃室加涡轮驱动燃料泵
And we can also couple the fuel rich preburner turbine with the fuel rich pump.
这样就不用去搞那么复杂的且对发动机复用极其不友好的密封装置了
So at least we don't have to deal with extremely elaborate seals
that are cantankerous and difficult for reusability
因为密封装置需要在每次飞行后进行探查与维护
as they might require inspections and maintenance after each flight.
但全流量分级燃烧循环最大的优点可能并不是气气反应
But perhaps the biggest advantage of full flow staged combustion
isn't just the gas, gas interaction,
也不是泵与涡轮之间相对简单的密封
or the relatively simple seals between the pumps and turbines,
而是预燃室内的温度
but it's also the temperatures inside the preburners.
想理解我说的 可以先来回顾一下富氧分级燃烧发动机
I think a good way for this to click is by studying the oxidizer rich staged combustion engine.
观察所有从泵直接进入主燃烧室的燃料
Look at all the at fuel going straight from the pump into the combustion chamber.
如果在那段燃料流量中加入少量氧化剂
What if we basically added just a dash of oxidizer to that stream of fuel
并安装另一个预燃室辅助驱动泵
and added another preburner to help power the pumps.
那么它就可以分担另一个预燃室要做的功 减轻其压力
It could share the load and decrease the amount of work the other preburner would have to do.
两个预燃室可以把驱动泵要做的功平摊下来
The two preburners would basically be splitting the work needed to run the pumps.
机械功率相同情况下 涡轮要做的功越少 预燃室内的压力与热量就越小
The less work the turbines need to do means less heat and pressure necessary inside the preburner
to do the same amount of mechanical work.
我们讲的再深入一点
But let's actually dive into this even more to help drill it in.
观察这个热能的公式
Take a look at this equation for thermal energy.
当前某种角度上 热能和动能共同构成了内能
Now, for some perspective here, thermal energy and kinetic energy make up internal energy,
也就是焓公式里的E
which is that E in the Enthalpy equation.
我接下来会告诉大家不同发动机循环模式下预燃室内温度的不同
And we're going to show you exactly
how different the temperatures inside the preburners of different engine cycle types can be.
别怕 抱紧我 一看公式我心里也打怵
Now bear with me, even seeing an equation on screen terrifies me,
我尽量说得简单点
but we'll make this as simple as possible.
我们要假设一台发动机的一些参数 才能知道那些变量怎么填
First we need to make up an engine, so we can figure out how to fill in all the variables.
假设我们要设计一款液氧甲烷发动机 轮轴功率25兆瓦
So let's say we're designing a methalox engine that requires 25 MW of shaft power
用来驱动一台100吨推力的发动机的泵
in order to power the pumps for a 100 tonne thrust engine.
我们想了解以下几种发动机循环中涡轮的温度差异
We want to find the difference in temperature at the turbine
它们是 富氧闭式循环 富燃闭式循环 和全流量分级燃烧循环
between an oxygen-rich close cycle engine,
a fuel rich close cycle engine and a full flow staged combustion cycle engine.
在发动机推力和室压相同的情况下 全流量循环能带来哪些优势?
What advantage would full flow actually give us
assuming the engines thrust and chamber pressure were kept the same?
25兆瓦的轮轴功率基本是预燃室内的全部热能了
That 25 MW of required shaft power is pretty much entirely thermal energy in the preburner,
而热能等于流经涡轮的燃料与氧化剂质量 乘燃料的比热 乘温度的变化值
which is equal to the mass flow of the propellants of the turbine
times the specific heat of those propellants times △T or the change in temperature.
发动机和燃料的种类已知 所以流过的质量和比冲都是已知量
Mass flow and specific heat are both known variables based on the engine and preopellants,
直接填入即可
so we can just plug those in.
把公式中温度变化量留在一侧
By rearranging our equation to solve for △T or change in temperature,
会发现温度的变化值等于热能 除以 流过的质量与比冲的乘积
we'll find the change in temperature is equal to the thermal energy
divided by the mass flow rate times the specific heat.
大家可能发现富氧闭式循环和富燃闭式循环中 流过涡轮的质量差异很大
Now you may notice there's a big difference in mass flow through the turbine
between oxygen-rich closed cycle and fuel rich closed cycle,
因为我们不仅需要考虑燃料和氧化剂的密度
because we needed to take into account not only the density of each propellant,
还要考虑发动机的燃料-氧化剂的混合比
but also the engine's fuel to oxidizer ratio.
总之这些数值对于不同循环来说已经八九不离十了
But these are good enough rough numbers for each of the system types.
注意到 对于全流量分级燃烧循环来说
The biggest thing to notice is that full flow staged combustion cycle
它拥有最大的流经涡轮的燃料与氧化剂质量
has the most mass of propellant flowing through the turbines
因为全部的燃料和氧化剂都会流经涡轮 毕竟人家叫"全流量"
because it has ALL of the propellant flowing through them, hence "Full Flow".
不但如此 全流量循环还可以沾点燃料和氧化剂的平均比热容的光
Not only that, full flow also gets to take advantage of the average specific heat of both propellants,
不过要说明的是 这个平均不是对半分
and not to get too confusing here, it's not just a 50 / 50 average,
需要考虑燃料和氧化剂的密度
but we have to account for the propellant densities,
燃料和氧化剂各自的热流量 发动机的氧化剂-燃料混合比
each propellant's respective heat flows, engine oxidizer fuel ratio,
甚至是两个轮轴各自的功率需求
and even the exact power demands of each shaft.
综上 在我们的例子中 对于涡轮处的温度变化
In our example, the change in temperature at the turbine
富氧闭式循环是全流量循环的近两倍
is nearly twice as much in oxygen-rich close cycle compared to full flow,
富燃闭式循环是全流量循环的近三倍
and three times as much in fuel rich close cycle compared to full flow.
非常强
That's impressive.
火箭工程师看到这做梦都能笑醒
This is a dream come true for rocket engineers,
因为发动机涡轮的热负荷通常是系统中最大的限制
as the turbine heat load is often one of the biggest limitations in the system.
当然了 现实中这一切都还要看燃料类型 发动机功率等各种变量
Now, of course, this all varies drastically by propellant type,
engine output and all sorts of other variables,
但希望我的例子能让大家对全流量循环的优势有一个总体的概念
but in general, our example helps illustrate full flow's biggest advantage.
即工程师可以选择让推力保持不变 大大降低涡轮的温度
But what this means is engineers can either reach their power levels
at much lower temperatures in their turbines,
也可以选择让系统直面热负荷 从而继续压榨发动机的推力
or they could potentially increase the power of their engines
assuming they've designed a system that can handle high heat loads,
或者选择两种情况的折中
or of course some happy compromise of both.
所以你既可以选择更高的室压
So you can either have more main chamber pressure,
也可以让泵工作在更低的压力下
or you can have the pumps, uh, put less stress on the pumps.
不过对于SpaceX的猛禽发动机来说
Although looking at SpaceX's Raptor engine,
他们更倾向于压榨出它的每一点性能
they like to push it all as much as possible for the ultimate performance.
全流量循环虽然有工程师眼中如此耀眼的优势
But as attractive as the positive attributes of full flow are to engineers,
但还是因其极端的复杂度让无数人望而却步 感觉不值
it's often considered not worth it, because of its extreme complexity.
各种管路交错纵横
With everything intertwined and interconnected,
发动机上一点点小改变都能对整体产生巨大的连锁反应
one small change in one part of the engine
can have this huge ripple effect on absolutely everything else.
猛禽发动机有一套液氧的动力头和一套燃料的动力头
powerhead/powerpack 动力头/动力包
指涡轮泵与预燃室及其附属设备的总成
国内一般叫"半系统"
In the case of Raptor, you've got an oxygen power head and a fuel power head.
很明显 它们使用的是不同的轮轴
And they're different shafts, um, obviously,
对应两个涡轮和预燃室
and you've got two turbines and two preburners.
两者互相还有燃气的交输
So, and, they're cross feeding one another.
因此 相比梅林发动机 猛禽发动机的启动程序极其复杂
So the start sequence for Raptor is insanely complicated,
compared to the start sequence for Merlin.
这一切就好像是在燃料和液氧动力头之间的刀尖上跳舞一样
Everything's it's, it's this basically, you're doing this delicate dance
between the fuel power head and the oxygen power head.
两者一旦同步上出问题
And if they get outta sync, uh, then,
正常是极度富氧/富燃状态的
预燃室可能就跑到理想燃烧比 直接被烧穿或炸烂了
then you can go stoichiometric in the preburner and melt or explode the preburners.
这意味着管理好阀门的开闭时间 发动机的启动甚至节流 难度都非常大
This means managing the timing of valves, startup, and even throttling is extremely hard to master,
裤裆里没点真家伙是搞不定的
and requires some very deep pockets to perfect,
也因此 研发出来的全流量循环发动机都很少
which is why we haven't seen that many full flow engines developed.
苏联还是拔得头筹 研发出了首款全流量分级燃烧循环发动机
As usual, the Soviets were the first to develop a full flow staged combustion engine,
有请 RD-270
the incredible RD-270.
偏二甲肼与四氧化二氮
该款发动机使用自燃燃料 非常巨大
This engine ran on hypergolic propellants and was massive.
推力只比土星五号的F-1发动机小15%
It was only about 15%, less powerful than the F-1 that powered, the Saturn V,
效率却高得多
yet it was far more efficient.
可惜它从来没上过天
Unfortunately it never saw flight
因为本来要用它的火箭 UR-700和UR-900都黄了
as the massive UR-700 and UR-900 it was proposed to power were never given the green light.
美国也在九十年代研发了全流量分级燃烧循环发动机的涡轮泵
The United States also developed the turbo pumps of a full flow stage combustion cycle engine in the 90s
称为"集成动力头试件"
called the "Itegrated Powerhead Demonstrator."
洛克达因公司成功完成了动力头的全工况试车
Aerojet and Rocketdyne were successful in reaching full capacity of the power pack,
但完整的发动机再没继续造
but it would never make it onto a full engine.
今天 SpaceX的猛禽发动机使用了全流量分级燃烧循环
Today, SpaceX is utilizing the full flow staged combustion cycle on their Raptor engines
未来将助力自家的星舰与超重型助推
that power their Starship and SuperHeavy booster.
全流量循环如此复杂
This all sounds so complicated,
需要两个预燃室和一系列复杂的工程设计才能实现
it needs two preburners and an insane amount of engineering to make it run.
有没有可能干脆不要预燃室呢?
What if you could just get rid of the preburners altogether?
其实还有两种泵压式发动机可以做到
Well, there's actually two pump fed engine types that do exactly that.
听我道来
Okay. So hear me out.
我们在主燃烧室内壁上开个孔
What if we just punched a hole in the side of the combustion chamber
能不能用冒出来的高压燃气驱动涡轮泵呢?
and just took that high pressure gas and used that to spin the turbines to run the pumps?
嗯 行得通
Hmm. Now there's an idea.
这就是抽气循环
This is essentially what the tap-off cycle or combustion tap-off cycle is.
可以拿掉又复杂又笨重的预燃室或燃气发生器
You can remove the complication and weight of having a preburner or gas generator
只使用主燃烧室的压力
and just use the main combustion pressure.
而发动机上被打了个洞 所以会损失一点点性能
You only lose a little bit of performance by having basically punched a hole in your engine,
但却能显著降低发动机的复杂度
but you free up a lot of complexity for sure.
它最有意思的是可以实现自我调节
The coolest thing is they can be fairly self-regulating
因为可以用风门来控制涡轮受到的压力
because you can limit the amount of pressure the turbine sees with a choke
即调整通往涡轮的管路的收窄程度
or by how much you shrink down the throat leading to the turbine.
难点在于 主燃烧室温度非常非常高
The problem is the main combustion chamber gets really really hot
又没有什么移动部件
because it doesn't have any moving parts,
所以通常使用燃料流经室壁进行再生冷却
and they're usually regenerative cooled with fuel running through the walls.
主燃烧室的温度可以达到3500K左右
The main combustion chamber can see temperatures of around 3,500 kelvin,
对于涡轮来说太高了
and that's far too hot for a turbine.
所以工程师会在燃气到达涡轮之前进行稀释降温
So engineers will sometimes need to dilute the gas before it reaches the turbine.
通常是使用额外的燃料让废气富燃 顺便降低温度
Usually with some additional fuel that will help lower the temperature
by making that exhaust more fuel rich.
之后废气可以直接排出
Then the exhaust can either just be dumped overboard
或者在压力降低后仍高于喷管某点的压力 且温度更低的时候重新引入喷管
or could be reintroduced into the nozzle at a point
where it's both higher pressure after its pressure losses and lower temperature
充当膜冷却使用
than the main combustion to be used as film cooling.
至今还没有抽气循环的发动机入轨 但技术在很多著名的发动机上都用到过
To date, no tap-off engine has made it to orbit, but it has been used on multiple notable engines
在60年代 NASA将土星五号的J-2发动机拿出来
In the 60s, NASA developed a follow up to the J-2 engine on the Saturn V
研发出了J-2简化版 或称J-2S发动机
known as the J-2 simplified or just J-2S for short.
正如其名 使用抽气循环后的发动机更加简化 且性能更强
As the name implies, it was meant to be simpler and higher performance by using the tap-off cycle.
虽然它的研发已经完成 但从未上过天
Now, although it was fully developed, it would never actually see flight.
蓝色起源新薛帕德火箭使用的BE-3发动机也是抽气循环
Blue Origin utilizes the tap-off cycle on their BE-3 engine that powers their New Shepherd rocket
萤火虫公司Alpha火箭的使用抽气循环的Reaver和Lightning发动机
and Firefly could be the first rocket to reach orbit with their tap-off cycle
可能会让他们成为首个入轨的抽气循环发动机
Reaver and Lightning engine on their Alpha rocket.
还有一种泵压式发动机不需要燃气发生器或预燃室
But there's still one more system that has pumps,
but doesn't need a gas generator or a preburner.
那就是膨胀循环
And that's the expander cycle.
火箭发动机对热量真的是又爱又恨
Remember how heat is both our enemy and our friend in rocket engines?
有意思的是 我们可以利用火箭发动机的热量来运行发动机
Well, there's one really cool thing we can do with the heat of the engine, and that's run the engine.
用发动机的热量运行发动机?啥玩意?
Wait, with the heat of the engine, we can run the engine? What the heck?!
隆重介绍膨胀循环 利用燃料和氧化剂的热能
This is called the expander cycle, and it harnesses the thermal energy of the fuel or the oxidizer,
通常是燃料 来冷却发动机
but most often the fuel, that is used to cool the engine.
同样 看过那期《火箭发动机冷却方法介绍》的朋友可能记得
Again, for those of you who watch my, "Why don't rocket engines melt" video know,
冷却发动机的一种常用且高效的方法
a very common and extremely effective way to cool a rocket engine
就是让燃料流经主燃烧室和喷管的侧壁内
is to actually pump the fuel through the walls of the combustion chamber and nozzle
to help keep them cool.
在冷却室壁的过程中
In the process of cooling the walls,
燃烧室内的热量会转移给燃料
the heat from the combustion chamber will be transferred into the fuel
燃料会吸收一部分热能
where it will absorb some of that heat energy.
有些燃料的吸热能力很强
Some fuels can take on heat better than others.
这种情况下氢就是很好的选择 因为它的比热容很高
And in this sense, hydrogen is a very good fuel because of its heat capacity.
在其他发动机循环中
In all the other engine cycles,
燃料通常以高温燃气的形式泵入主燃烧室
this fuel is usually just pumped into the combustion chamber as a hot gas,
之后通常会与液态氧化剂反应
which usually has to interact then with a liquid oxidizer.
但在膨胀循环中
But in the case of the expander cycle,
其实可以使用这部分热量驱动涡轮
we can actually take this heat energy and use that to spin the turbine.
但还有几个问题要解决
But there's a few problems.
首先还是和其它发动机一样的鸡生蛋蛋生鸡的问题
This engine, again, like all the other engines, has a big chicken and egg syndrome.
如果发动机没热起来 泵就没法转
If the engine isn't hot, then how does it even power the pumps?
所以我未来肯定会出一期视频讲发动机的启动
Well, again, we definitely need to do a video on how to start a rocket engine,
通常发动机需要另一种能量源先让泵达到转速
because, they often require a second source to get the pumps up to speed,
等其余一切达到运行温度后 发动机才能维持运转
and get everything up to operational temperatures before they can run on their own.
同时 因为系统总热量有限 发动机的推力输出也是有限的
But it's also limited in thrust output based on the total amount of heat energy available in the system.
可以这样想 随着发动机一点点变大
Think about it this way, as the engine grows,
流过系统的燃料也会增加
the amount of fuel flowing through the system increases too.
而其中流经燃烧室壁的燃料也会增加它们的冷却能力
That increase in fuel running through the walls also increases the cooling capacity,
这点是好事
which normally is a good thing.
但是注意到当燃烧室体积变大的时候
But couple that with the fact that when you increase a chamber,
表面积是正比于半径的平方增长的
this surface area goes up by the square of the radius,
而体积是随半径的立方增长的
while the volume goes up by the cube.
所以实际上火箭发动机越大越容易冷却
This means it's actually easier to cool a large rocket engine
than it is to cool a small rocket engine.
这也是气尖喷管发动机的主要难点之一 看过我那期视频的应该记得
av841875408
感谢@长五遥三没有鸽
This is one of the main problems with Aerospike engines like we discussed in my video about Aerospikes.
同样的情况还会导致驱动涡轮泵的能量受限
This same situation is what limits the amount of a available energy
that can be used to spin the pumps.
发动机推力越大 泵就需要越多的能量
A bigger and more powerful engine needs more energy to run the pumps.
而发动机体积与推力的增加 并没有同比例增加流经室壁的可加热的燃料量
And that same larger and more powerful engine
doesn't actually heat up the same percentage of fuel flowing through it.
所以实际上膨胀循环发动机的推力有限
So there is a limit to how powerful it can actually be.
同样 和闭式循环发动机类似
And similar to closed cycle engines,
燃料在到达涡轮之前压力要足够高
the pressure needs to be quite high before it hits the turbine.
有了高压力才能流过涡轮 而这会带来一次压力降低
It needs to be high enough that it can go through the turbine, which will cause a pressure drop,
我们需要经过压降后的燃料压力还能显著高于主燃烧室室压
and it still will need to be a decent amount higher pressure than the main combustion chamber.
因此燃料泵需要足够强大 才能让燃料达到需求的压力
This means the fuel pump needs to really do a lot of work
to get the fuel up to those kinds of pressures.
放到通常使用的液氢燃料
And if it's say liquid hydrogen, like it normally is,
那就得上超大的多级泵 压力才能达标
you'd better believe that's going to be a huge pump with lots of stages
in order to get the pressure high enough.
对于只用一个涡轮的液氢液氧发动机来说
In the case of a hydrogen fueled engine with a single turbine,
工程师在涡轮泵内可能还需要加装齿轮箱
engineers might even need to employ a gearbox inside the turbo pump,
让氢泵达到足够的转速 提供足够的能量
so they can direct the required amount of speed and energy to the fuel pumps,
同时 氧泵相比之下需要的能量就没那么多
and send less to the oxygen pump, which doesn't require nearly as much energy.
没有预燃室 确实简单高效了 但又要应付复杂的活动部件
So now you've again traded one form of simplicity and efficiency
for another complication and more moving parts.
不过高效是真的高效
But it is very efficient and it's an effective way
使用系统中几乎免费的热量作为能量来源驱动泵 太妙了
to use what is basically free energy in the system, heat, to power your pumps. It's genius.
现实中的实例有即将到来的Ariane 6火箭上面级使用的Vinci发动机
Some examples are the upcoming Vinci engine that will power the upper stage of the Ariane 6,
宇宙神5火箭半人马上面级的RL-10发动机
the RL-10 engine that powers the Centaur upper stage for the Atlas V,
它还会用来驱动SLS的上面级
and it will also power the SLS's upper stage.
这些发动机的效率高得离谱
These engines can reach ludicrous levels of efficiency.
实际上 使用膨胀循环的氢氧机RL-10B2比冲高达462秒
In fact, the RL-10B2, which utilizes the expander cycle with hydrolox propellants
reaches 462 seconds of specific impulse.
几乎触碰到了化学火箭比冲的天花板
This is about the upper limits of what's even possible for chemical rocket engines.
膨胀循环有一个分支叫膨胀排放循环
But there is another version of the expander cycle called the expander bleed cycle.
燃料推动涡轮后不再注入主燃烧室 系统可以更加简单
It makes the system a little bit simpler by not putting the fuel back into the combustion chamber
after its spun the turbine.
这样可以利用更多的压强来驱动涡轮
This means you can actually use more of the pressure in the heat to spin the pumps,
而不用在乎过了涡轮后压力要比主燃烧室高这件事了
and it doesn't need to be higher pressure than the combustion chamber.
只需要用一小部分受热膨胀的燃料 然后排放掉
So it'll just use a little bit of the expanded hot gas and throw it overboard.
虽然有点浪费燃料 但效率仍然很高
Although it's going to be a little bit of a waste of fuel, it's still very efficient.
这样还可以解决推力受限的问题
This can help overcome the limitations of thrust
因为可以用上更多有限的压力和热量来驱动涡轮泵
since you can use more of the limited pressure and heat available to power the pumps.
牺牲一点效率 换来了推力的增加与复杂度的降低
So it trades a little bit of efficiency for the potential of increased thrust and decreased complexity.
膨胀排放循环的实例不多
There aren't a lot of examples of the expander bleed cycle,
能想到的有蓝色起源未来新格伦火箭上面级的BE-3U发动机
other than the BE-3U that will power the upper stage of Blue Origin's upcoming New Glenn rocket,
还有日本H1 H2和未来H3火箭的LE-5A和LE-5B发动机
and the LE-5A and LE-5B on Japan's H1, H2 and their upcoming H3 rockets.
膨胀循环还有个分支叫双膨胀循环
There's also another version of the expander cycle called the dual expander cycle
同时使用燃料和氧化剂为燃烧室壁再生制冷
that utilizes both the fuel and oxidizer
assuming that both those propellants are used to regeneratively to cool the chamber.
到这 所有主流的发动机循环类型就讲差不多了
Okay, but really those are the major engine cycle types.
我们一起总结回顾 举一反三一下吧
So let's wrap this up with a little overview and a few more thoughts.
说到头 也找不到所谓"最好"的循环类型
At the end of the day, there is no best cycle type.
每种都有自己独特的驱动发动机的方法
Each and every system has a unique way to power a rocket engine,
但就像火箭上的每个系统一样 一切都是有得必有失
but like all things rockets, there are trade offs and compromises to each and every system.
你发动机性能再强 不可靠又有什么用?
Because who cares how high performance your engine is if it's not reliable.
挤压式发动机确实优雅简洁
There's definitely the elegance and ease of pressure fed engines,
可性能上不去
but their performance is limited.
电动泵循环目前是一颗冉冉升起的新星
Meanwhile, the electric pumped cycle is seeing a new rise in popularity
因为锂电池能量密度增加 材料科学也有了进步
with the increased density of lithium based batteries and more advanced material science.
燃气发生器循环仍然是航天圈的扛把子
The gas generator cycle is still one of the most common cycle types
结构相对简单 性能却很强
and it blends a very healthy amount of performance and relative simplicity.
整体上感觉非常折中
It seems to be a great all around compromise.
闭式循环也有很多追随者 苏联让人误以为它很简单
Closed cycle has always been much sought after and the Soviet's made it look easy.
比开式循环性能强 但会有额外的复杂度与新的难点
Gains over open cycle engines should be expected, but with extra complexity and some new issues.
全流量分级燃烧循环 轻松拿下复杂度第一名
Full flow is easily the most complex system,
但却能用最冷的涡轮带最热的燃烧室
but has the potential to run the coolest turbines and the hottest chamber,
轻松把推力抬到新台阶
which can definitely help it reach ridiculous levels of thrust.
抽气循环 我其实很惊讶人类在这方面研发投入不多
Tap-off, I'm actually surprised we haven't seen developed more.
它又是如此的简单 可靠
It seems like it's again, relatively simple and reliable,
却还能达到相当高的性能
but it can actually still reach high levels of performance.
膨胀循环 老强了 RL-10的本事无需多言
Expander cycle is awesome, and has proven to be a great choice on the RL-10,
但推力实在有限
but it does have its limitations on thrust output,
通常需要一个助推级把它先送上天才行
which often leaves it off the table for a booster engine.
还有一些把这些循环类型混起来用的
There are also a few options of mixing and matching cycle types,
比如燃料侧使用燃气发生器 氧化剂侧使用膨胀循环
like using a gas generator on just the fuel side, and the expander cycle to power the oxidizer side,
或许还有其他工程师们能想到的 但还没公之于众的独特组合
or some unique combinations that engineers have come up with,
but haven't really seen the light of day yet.
但驱动发动机的方法也就这些了
But yeah, that's how you power a rocket engine.
本期视频让你理解这些循环类型了吗?
Did this video help you understand all the different cycle types?
欢迎大家在评论区讨论
Let me know if you have any other questions or thoughts in the comments below.
未来我还会开离子推进或核动力火箭发动机等话题的视频
And in the future, we'll cover more exotic options like ion propulsion or nuclear rocket engines,
因为我觉得 它们值得被世人知晓
because in my opinion, each of those deserves their own dedicated video.
再次无比感谢我的赞助者们让这期视频
这个频道成为可能
As always, I owe a huge thank you to my
Patreon supporters for helping make videos like this,
再次无比感谢我的赞助者们让这期视频 这个频道成为可能
and everything else we do at Everyday Astronaut possible.
如果你想加入我们独家Discord群 想看些限定直播
If you want to gain access to our awesome Discord community or some extra live streams,
或者只是想看看幕后内容
or just some fun behind the scenes content,
欢迎去patreon.com/everydayastronaut赞助我
head on over to patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
希望网上冲浪的还可以来我的网店看看
And while you're online, be sure and check out our awesome web store for things like this,
比如这件全流量分级燃烧循环帽衫
our full flow staged combustion cycle hoodie,
背后还印着特别帅的原理图
which also has a cool schematic on the back,
还有其他火箭原理图合集 未来火星人合集 苏联发动机合集
along with the rest of our schematics collection, our Future Martian collection or our Soviet collection.
店里好玩的老多了 欢迎来看看
There's lots of really fun stuff over at everydayastronaut.com/shop.
感谢大家 我是《天天太空人》的Tim Dodd
Thanks everybody. That's gonna do it for me. I'm Tim DOD, the Everyday Astronaut,
把航天知识带给寻常百姓家~
bringing space down to earth for everyday people.